Guide to the Job Clark Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Job Clark papers
1810-1882
MS 18
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.25
(5 boxes)
Notebooks of an early student at the Yale Medical School (ca.1815) on lectures by Silliman, Ives & Smith; notebooks on his medical practice; medical reference and prescription notebooks; Ravenna, Ohio, meteorological journals; miscellaneous medical notes and printed material. An addition to the collection comprises personal correspondence of Job Clark and family members, as well as journal entries and writings.
Clark, Job
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Sheldon DeForest Clark, 1968; gift of Sheldon DeForest, Dr. Lucy Swanton Clark, and Jared A. Clark, 2011.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Job Clark Papers consist of notes, writings, and printed material (1810-1858) relating primarily to the Yale Medical School and the practice of medicine. Clark is listed in the Catalogue of the Medical School of 1815. His medical notes on lectures by Benjamin Silliman, Eli Ives, and Nathan Smith, 1815-1816, are particularly valuable as they relate to the earliest period of medical school history--the Medical Institution was organized August 31, 1813. An addition to the collection focuses more broadly on the entire Clark family and comprises personal correspondence of its members, as well as journal entries and writings, describing their daily lives and interactions.
Biographical / Historical
Job Clark grew up in Westfield, Massachusetts, and married Ruth Sheldon of that town. After attending the Yale Medical School in 1815 and 1816, he served as Surgeon's Mate with the Militia of Massachusetts until 1824. Clark later moved to Ravenna, Ohio, where he raised his family and practiced medicine until his death.
Medicine -- United States; Medicine; Meteorology; Ravenna (Ohio); Diaries; Physicians; Clark, Job; Ives, Eli, 1779-1861; Silliman, Benjamin, 1779-1864; Smith, Nathan, 1762-1829; Yale University -- Students; Yale University. School of Medicine -- History
- Inventory
  - Fragment of a diary, 1815 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Meterorological Journal, Ravenna Portage Co., Ohio, 1834, 1841-1842, 1847, 1852-1858 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Note on series of discourses on systematic theology, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Admission cards to lectures in medicine and natural philosophy at Yale College, 1815 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Invitation card to Commencement Ball of Williams College, 1810 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Class notebooks on diseases and their treatment, 1814-1816 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lecture notebook of medical instruction by Drs. Silliman, Smith, and Ives; 224 p., 1815-1817 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Book of Reference and General Principles, indexed, 1819-1821 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Booklets and single pages with information related to his medical practice, 1819-1837, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Medical diary of cases, 1836 November-1837 November (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Notebook of prescriptions and treatments, indexed, 1816 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Notebook with pharmaceutical prescriptions, 1819, 1824 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Additional Material, 1813-1882; Accession 2012-M-015
  Arrangement
  Materials are arranged alphabetically by personal name, then by type of material, and chronologically therein.
  Scope and Contents
  Primary correspondents are Clark family members: Job and Ruth (Sheldon) Clark, son Charles, daughters Cornelia, Elizabeth, and Frances, and extended family members, and to a lesser extent, friends and acquaintances. The majority of the correspondence was identified by Lucy Swanton Clark and is in envelopes prepared by her with the name of the author, recipient, and date.
  - Clark, Charles (son of Job Clark)
    - Correspondence, outgoing
      - 1841-1848 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
      - 1849-1858 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
    - Correspondence, incoming
      - 1850-1855, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Nutting, R., 1853 July 25 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Clark, Elizabeth (Lizzie/Libby)
    - Correspondence, outgoing, 1848 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, incoming, 1838-1870, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, incoming (Elizabeth and Cornelia), Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Writings, Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Presumably the handwriting of Elizabeth, includes copies of poems, rules for a game, etc.
  - Clark, Francis
    - Correspondence, incoming, 1850s-1860s (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Clark, Job
    - Correspondence, outgoing, 1813-1851 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, incoming, 1813-1840s (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Financial, 1821, 1862-1864 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Journal, handwritten, Circa 1820s (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Journal transcripts, 1812, 1818, circa 1850s (Box 3, Folder 8)
        Typed transcriptions of journal entries were prepared by Lucy Swanton Clark.
    - Writings, 1817, 1820s, 1835, undated (Box 3, Folder 9-11)
      Topics are varied, including botany, intemperance, and sermon texts.
  - Clark, Mary S., 1858, 1878
    - Correspondence, incoming, 1858, 1878 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Clark, Ruth
    - Correspondence, incoming, 1825, 1867 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Writings, Circa 1820s (Box 3, Folder 14-15)
  - Others
    - Correspondence, outgoing/incoming
      - ''Aunt", 1867, 1876 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - ''Brother and Sister", 1858 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - "Family", Undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - "Father", Undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - ''Friend(s)", 1868-1869 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - ''Grandma", 1874 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - "R", 1882 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - "Sister", 1855-1874 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - "Son", 1850 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - "Tappan, L. P.", 1843, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Unidentified, Undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Transcriptions of selected correspondence of family members, 1813-1850, 1857, undated (Box 4, Folder 4-9)
    Typed transcriptions were prepared by Lucy Swanton Clark.